Finding Aid for the Slee Family Collection, 1893-1981
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Slee Family Collection, 1893-1981
Mus. Arc. 12.2
Slee family
3 boxes (90 items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Collection contains clippings, obituaries, correspondence, eighteen photographs of Alice and Frederick Slee, family, and friends, writings by Frederick Slee, documents about the Slee Bequest to the University of Buffalo, concert programs, and a log of a twenty-one day sailing trip undertaken by Frederick Slee and two friends in 1914. The log details their adventures along the northern shore of Lake Ontario.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the library by faculty member, Stephen Manes, who received it from Ansie Baird (Mrs. Brent Baird). Mrs. Baird received the collection from Charles G. Beaudette. Some clippings and programs were added by Music Library staff subsequent to the receipt of the collection.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Entire collection digitized and available in UB Libraries Digital Collections.
Biographical Note
Frederick Caldecott Slee (1870-1954), was a successful corporate lawyer in Buffalo, N.Y. His two passions in life were sailing and Beethoven. While at Harvard pursuing his law degree, Mr. Slee also studied music theory and composition. He later furthered his music education at the Sorbonne, in Paris. Mr. Slee and his wife Alice were devoted fans of chamber music and the music of Beethoven, especially the string quartets. They built a special music room in their Saybrook Place home with a raised platform for performers. The room was used most Sundays for recitals with friends. Mr. Slee was an accomplished musician, playing viola, violin, piano and the cello.
Alice Slee, née McDonald, was born August 20, 1875 in East Aurora, NY. She moved to Buffalo to attend business school. It was there that Alice met and married Frederick Slee in 1905. Mrs. Slee was active in many worthy causes, serving the Red Cross through the two World Wars. Mrs. Slee was honored as one of Western New York's outstanding citizens by the Buffalo News in 1952. Mrs. Slee was also devoted to the music of Beethoven and sponsored concerts for all of Buffalo to enjoy. Mrs. Slee passed away exactly two years after her husband on May 19, 1956.
The Slee Bequest at the University at Buffalo provides for the annual performance of all of Beethoven's string quartets in an order prescribed by Frederick Slee. The concert series dates to 1955 and has featured some of the most renowned string quartets, including the Budapest, Guarnieri, Juilliard, Cleveland, Tokyo, Emerson, and Concord quartets. The Music Department at The State University of Buffalo administers the Slee Bequest and the annual series of concerts are held in Slee Concert Hall located at the University. The endowment also funds the Slee professorship in the Music Department.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains various documents pertaining to the lives of Frederick Caldecott Slee and his wife, Alice, including music-related writings by Frederick Slee, correspondence, clippings about the Slees, documents concerning the Slee Bequest to the University of Buffalo, and concert programs. The collection contains eighteen photographs of friends and family. The majority of the family photographs are of Frederick C. Slee and his wife, Alice. There are two photographs of Slee's Sunday morning string quartet, taken in his music room, and a photograph of the Slee home at 59 Saybrook Place in Buffalo.
One of the highlights of the collection is a typewritten daily log of a sailing trip taken in 1914, by Frederick C. Slee and his friends, George T. Moseley and Louis Wright Simpson. The log includes 46 leaves, with 30 photographs taken during their three week journey. The author of this log was also the purser, Louis Wright Simpson. Frederick Slee signed on as Captain, and Mr. George Moseley was the yacht's Mate. Mr. Slee and his companions left the Buffalo Yacht Club, beginning their trip on Lake Erie. The second day they traveled through the Welland Canal to Lake Ontario. Most of their time was spent sailing the northern shoreline of Lake Ontario. Many of the photographs show life aboard the Althea: hoisting the sails, cleaning up after cooking, and taking turns behind the wheel. The sailing trip commenced on July 11, 1914 and ended on August 1, 1914. The first world news they saw after twenty-one carefree days was the newspaper headline, "Germany Declares War", the beginning of World War I.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series:
I. Log of the Good Yacht Althea on the Summer Cruise of 1914
II. Photographs
III. Writings of Frederick Slee
IV. Correspondence
V. Clippings
VI. Slee Bequest Documents
VII. Programs
Container List
- Log of the Good Yacht Althea on the Summer Cruise of 1914, July 11-August 1, 1914, I.; Item 1
  - Log of the Good Yacht Althea on the Summer Cruise of 1914, July 11-August 1, 1914, 46 typescript leaves; 28 cm. (Box 1, Item 1)
    Contains thirty 2 x 3 inch snapshots taken during the voyage. Participants were Frederick Slee, George T. Mosley, and Louis Wright Simpson. The logbook was written by Simpson.
    The entire logbook is available online in UB Libraries Digital Collections. All of the thirty photographs in the logbook are individually described and available in the Slee Family Collection in UB Libraries Digital Collections.
- Photographs, circa 1900-1910, II.; Item 2-19
  Eighteen photographs of Slee family and friends.
  - Frederick Caldecott Slee, undated, 1 photograph; Beach, Howard (Box 1, Item slp002)
  - Frederick Caldecott Slee, 1910, 1 photograph; Nussbaumer (Box 1, Item slp003)
  - Alice Slee, undated, 1 photograph; Freres, Leon (Box 1, Item slp004)
  - John P. Seymour and Grace Gratten Collins, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp005)
  - Charles Gus Augustus Collins and Frederick Caldecott Slee, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp006)
  - Katie Simpson, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp007)
  - Grace Cotton Collins and Alice Slee, March 1908, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp008)
  - Alice Slee, March 1908, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp009)
  - Grace Gratten Collins, March 1908, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp010)
  - Alice Slee, March 1908, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp011)
  - Saybrook String Quartet: Isabelle Workman Evans, violin, Nicholas D'Addio, violoncello, Frederick Slee, viola, and George Kogler, violin, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp012)
  - Saybrook String Quartet: Isabelle Workman Evans, violin, Nicholas D'Addio, violoncello, Frederick Slee, viola, and George Kogler, violin, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp013)
  - Flooding river, unidentified location, undated, 1 photograph; Collins, Charles Augustus? (Box 1, Item slp014)
  - Canal lock (possibly Lockport, N.Y.), undated, 1 photograph; Collins, Charles Augustus? (Box 1, Item slp015)
  - Frederick Caldecott Slee in automobile, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp016)
  - Group of eleven boys, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp017)
  - Building, possibly in Buffalo, N.Y., undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp018)
  - Interior view of room, possibly in Slee home, undated, 1 photograph (Box 1, Item slp019)
- Writings of Frederick Slee, 1914-1938, III.; Item 20-28
  Roughly in chronological order.
  - From Wagner to Schoenberg 1914, Typescript (15 leaves) (Box 2, Item 20)
  - Untitled reminiscences, after 1924, Typescript with ms. additions ([26] leaves; numbered 4-6, 6 ½, 7-9, 9 ½, 9 1/2A, 10-19, 22-28) (Box 2, Item 21)
  - Concerts of Saybrook String Quartet, [programs and notes for concerts], November 1931-May 30, 1937, Typescript ([38] leaves; title page, 36 numbered leaves, with leaf 33 repeated) (Box 2, Item 22)
  - Saybrook String Quartet program, May 1938, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 23)
  - Saybrook String Quartet program, September 1938, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 24)
  - Saybrook String Quartet program, April 2, 1939, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 25)
  - Saybrook String Quartet program, April 30, 1939, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 26)
  - Saybrook String Quartet program, May 30, 1939, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 27)
  - Summary of Saybrook String Quartet repertoire, undated, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 28)
- Correspondence, 1896-circa 1938, IV.; Item 29-34
  - Original letter from Mrs. Alice Slee concerning repertoire of the Saybrook String Quartet, sent to audience members to solicit recommendations for future seasons. Marked with answers by unknown recipient, undated, Typescript with ms. additions (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 29)
  - Capen, Grace, undated, Manuscript (3 leaves) (Box 2, Item 30)
  - Perry, Elizabeth(?), undated, Manuscript (1 folded leaf) (Box 2, Item 31)
  - Silverman, Oscar, undated, Manuscript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 32)
  - Unidentified correspondent, undated, Manuscript (1 folded leaf) (Box 2, Item 33)
  - Apthorp, William F. to Frederick Slee, concerning program notes for Boston Symphony Orchestra concerts, October 29, 1896, Typescript (1 leaf) (Box 2, Item 34)
- Clippings, 1954-1981, V.; Item 35-41
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Obituary for Frederick Caldecott Slee, 1954 (Box 3, Item 35)
  - Obituary for Frederick Caldecott Slee, 1954 (Box 3, Item 36)
  - Buffalo Evening News November 12, 1954 (Box 3, Item 37)
    Report of Slee Bequest to the University of Buffalo (photocopy)
  - Buffalo Evening News October 1, 1955 (Box 3, Item 38)
    Article about first cycle of Beethoven string quartets performed by the Budapest Quartet.
  - Buffalo Evening News obituary for Alice Slee (photocopy), May 21, 1956 (Box 3, Item 39)
  - Buffalo Evening News article by John Dwyer about Frederick and Alice Slee and the twentieth anniversary of the Slee Beethoven String Quartet Cycle series, January 24, 1976 (Box 3, Item 40)
  - Buffalo Evening News, article by John Dwyer about Frederick and Alice Slee and the upcoming twenty-fifth season of the Slee Beethoven String Quartet Cycle series (photocopy), July 19, 1981 (Box 3, Item 41)
- Slee Bequest Documents, 1952-1981, VI.; Item 42-44
  - Last Will and Testament of Frederick C. and Alice Slee, October 1952, 3 leaves (Box 3, Item 42)
  - Letter to Alice Slee from Claude E. Puffer, Treasurer of the University of Buffalo, thanking Mrs. Slee for receipt of funds to cover expense of concert by the Budapest String Quartet, September 20, 1955, 1 leaf (Box 3, Item 43)
  - The proper usage of the Slee Bequest and its integration with other departmental resources, written by James McKinnon, The Music Department, SUNY at Buffalo, 1981, 14 leaves (Box 3, Item 44)
- Programs, 1894-2005, VII.; Item 45-90
  Arranged in seven subseries by location.
  - Slee Beethoven Quartet Series, 1955-2005, VII. A.; Item 45-48
    - Program for performance of Beethoven string quartets by the Budapest String Quartet, February 22, 1955, 2 leaves (photocopy); The concert was performed in memory of Frederick C. Slee. (Item 3, Item 45)
    - Program for concerts at Samuel P. Capen Hall at the University of Buffalo of Beethoven string quartets by the Budapest String Quartet, the first two concerts presented in the continuing Slee Beethoven String Quartet Cycle series, September 23 1955 and September 24, 1955., 2 leaves (photocopy) (Item 3, Item 46)
    - Program note booklet for twentieth consecutive playing of the Slee Beethoven Quartet Cycle, 1976, 7 pages; With notes written by John Dwyer. (Item 3, Item 47)
    - Fifty years of Beethoven, 1955-2005. Program booklet for Slee Beethoven Quartet Cycle, 2005-2006, 13 pages; With notes by Paul Katz. (Item 3, Item 48)
  - Boston, Cambridge, and Northampton, Massachusetts, 1894-1895, VII. B.; Item 49-70
    Alphabetically arranged by organization and then chronologically.
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University October 18, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 49)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University October 19, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 50)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University November 2, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 51)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University November 16, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 52)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University January 4, 1895, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 53)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University February 15, 1895, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 54)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University March 8, 1895, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 55)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University April 6, 1895, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 56)
    - Boston Symphony Orchestra, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University April 26, 1895, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 57)
    - Handel and Haydn Society, Boston Music Hall December 18, 1893, 5 pages (Item 3, Item 58)
    - Handel and Haydn Society, April 18, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 59)
    - Pierian Sodality of Harvard University, Radcliffe College May 10, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 60)
    - Harvard Glee Club, Pierian Sodality, Harvard Banjo Club, and Harvard Mandolin Club, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University May 17, 1894, 1 booklet (12 pages) (Item 3, Item 61)
    - Pierian Sodality and Mandolin Club of Harvard University, Assembly Hall, Smith College, Northampton, Massachusetts May 23, 1894, 1 folded leaf (Item 3, Item 62)
    - Pierian Sodality, Harvard Banjo Club, and Harvard Mandolin Club, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University December 18, 1894, 1 booklet (12 pages) (Item 3, Item 63)
    - Pierian Sodality, Harvard Banjo Club, and Harvard Mandolin Club, Sanders Theatre, Harvard University May 23, 1895, 1 booklet (11 pages) (Item 3, Item 64)
    - Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.), Mechanics Hall Auditorium (Boston, Mass.) February 27, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 65)
    - Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.), Mechanics Hall Auditorium (Boston, Mass.) March 2, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 66)
    - Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.): Concert program of selections from various operas, Mechanics Hall Auditorium (Boston, Mass.) March 4, 1894, 1 leaf; Performers include Nellie Melba. (Item 3, Item 67)
    - Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.), Mechanics Hall Auditorium (Boston, Mass.) March 9, 1894, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 68)
    - New York Symphony Orchestra, Walter Damrosch, conductor, Boston Theatre April 11-12, 1894?, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 69)
    - Sherwood, William H., b. 1854, Boston, 1895?, 1 booklet (6 pages) (Item 3, Item 70)
  - Buffalo (N.Y.), 1897-1933, VII. C.; Item 71-76
    - Buffalo Symphony Orchestra, Music Hall (Buffalo, N.Y.), January 7, 1897, 1 booklet (16 pages) (Item 3, Item 71)
    - Buffalo Symphony Orchestra, Music Hall (Buffalo, N.Y.), February 4, 1897, 1 booklet (14 pages) (Item 3, Item 72)
    - Buffalo Symphony Orchestra, Music Hall (Buffalo, N.Y.), February 3, 1898, 1 booklet (16 pages) (Item 3, Item 73)
    - Buffalo Symphony Orchestra, Music Hall (Buffalo, N.Y.), March 10, 1898, 1 booklet (16 pages) (Item 3, Item 74)
    - Twentieth Century Club (Buffalo, N.Y.): Song recital by Mr. and Mrs. Georg Henschel, November 26, [1897?], 1 booklet (8 pages) (Item 3, Item 75)
    - Twentieth Century Club (Buffalo, N.Y.): String quartet concert, March 24, 1933, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 76)
  - London (England), 1924, VII. D.; Item 77-80
    - Café Parisien, Hotel Savoy Menu, July 4, 1924, 1 folded leaf (Item 3, Item 77)
    - Worshipful Company of Musicians, Stationers Hall July 8, 1924, 1 leaf (Item 3, Item 78)
    - Worshipful Company of Musicians, Stationers Hall, July 8, 1924, 1 leaf; Diagram of banquet seating. (Item 3, Item 79)
    - Worshipful Company of Musicians, Stationers Hall: Concert program, July 8, 1924, 1 booklet (5 pages) (Item 3, Item 80)
  - New York (N.Y.), April 11-May 1910, VII. E.; Item 81
    - New Theatre (New York, N.Y.): Program for performance of Beethoven, a dramatic biography by René Fauchois, April 11-May 1910, 1 folded leaf (Item 3, Item 81)
  - Paris (France), May 1924-February 1925, VII. F.; Item 82-89
  - Rome (Italy), December 24, 1924, VII. G.; Item 90
    - Busch, Adolf, 1891-1952: Accademica di Santa Cecilia, December 24, 1924, 1 booklet (16 pages) (Item 3, Item 90)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Slee, Alice, 1875-1956; Slee, Frederick Caldecott, 1870-1954; Simpson, Louis Wright
Subjects
Logbooks--1911-1920; Slee family--Photographs; Yachting--Erie, Lake--Photographs; Yachting--Ontario, Lake (N.Y. and Ont.)--Photographs; Yachts--New York (State)--Buffalo--Photographs; Buffalo (N.Y.)--Photographs
Genres
Portraits; Photographs; Logs (records)
Associated Material
Related Resources
Frederick Caldecott Slee Collection of Manuscript Scores, 1890-1954
Mus. Arc. 12.1
The collection contains scores and parts of original compositions and arrangements by Frederick Slee. It also includes transcriptions of works by composers such as J.S. Bach, Mozart, and Haydn, as well as a lesson for recorder.